http://youtu.be/pBrghZ5XMr8
http://youtu.be/pBrghZ5XMr8 Tung Dinh - VGU
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Let's look at device communication.
Giờ ta sang phần giao tiếp của thiết bị
Let's say we have two devices, A and B, that want to communicate.
Giả sử ta có 2 thiết bị, A và B muốn giao tiếp
One of the things that we have to address in this communication
Một điều phải giải quyết trong giao tiếp này
is synchronization.
là đồng bộ hoá
Synchronization is simply a process by which
Đồng bộ hoá là quá trình
we bridge the speed mismatch between communicating devices.
mà ta nối các thiết bị không cùng tốc độ
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So if A is faster than B, or B is faster than A,
Vậy, nếu A nhanh hơn B, hoặc ngược lại
or they're the same speed it still works.
hoặc chúng cùng tốc độ, thì vẫn hoạt động chứ?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Yes.
Vâng
So let's take a few scenarios.
Vậy, ta giả sử vài trường hợp
When I talk about A and B, these could be, these devices could be computers,
Khi ta nói về A và B, nó có thể là là máy tính
for example a launch pad, a micro computer, a microcontroller.
ví dụ như mạch đang dùng, máy vi tính, mạch điện tử
It could be devices, like for example, the LCD
Nó cũng có thể là thiết bị, ví dụ LCD
device that we might be working with, or any other external device that's
mà ta đang dùng, hoặc bất kì thiết bị ngoại vi nào
connected.
mà nó kết nối
Or we can even think of this as an analogy
Hoặc ta có thể liên tưởng như phép so sánh
where we consider A and B to be people.
mà ta coi A và B như người
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So what happens if A talks a lot faster than B listens?
Vậy điều gì xảy ra nếu A nói nhnah hơn B có thể nghe
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So obviously there's going to be a miscommunication.
Hiển nhiên là rối loạn giao tiếp rồi
So what we need is a way for them to synchronize
Vậy điều ta cần là đồng bộ hoá
so that the communication is perfectly comprehensible to both parties.
vậy thì 2 phía đều có thể hiểu được
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: I can think of a problem.
Tôi nghĩ đến 1 vấn đề
You talk too fast, professor Yerraballi.
Anh nói nhanh đấy, giáo sư Yerraballi
If you slowed down I could understand you better.
Nếu anh nói chậm lại, tôi có thể hiểu tốt hơn
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Yes, so what you're saying
Vâng, ý anh là,
is if I am talking too fast then I should slow down.
nếu tôi nói nhanh quá, thì tôi nên nói chậm lại
So that I have to in some way know what-- there's a preset amount of time
Vậy bằng cách nào ta biết, có 1 khoảng thời gian định trước
that you want me to wait for before I say the next word or the next sentence.
mà anh muốn tôi chời trước khi nói từ tiếp theo
So we have our first form of device synchronization.
Vậy, ta có dạng đầu tiên của đồng bộ hoá thiết bị
We call this the blind cycle synchronization
gọi là blind cycle synchronization
where the device A will send a message to B
chỗ mà thiết bị A gửi tín hiệu cho B
and wait for a certain amount of time, some delta, predetermined delta t,
và đợi 1 khoảng thời gian định trước delta t
and then send the second message.
rồi mới gửi tín hiệu thứ 2
And then waits again a delta t amount of time and sends the third message.
và sau đó đợi delta t, rồi mới gửi cái thứ 3
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: It's called blind because the time you wait is fixed.
Nó gọi là blind, vì thời gian đợi cố định
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: And the time delta t
Và delta t
is usually determined by the device B's speed.
thì thông thường phụ thuộc vào tốc độ của B
Which means that A has to be aware of what B's configured speed is
nghĩa là A phải biết tốc độ của B
of processing and wait for that amount of time.
và phải chờ thời gian đó
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So the problem with blind is the speed of B may vary.
Vậy, vấn đề với blind là tốc độ của B có thể thay đổi
And so to make blind work, A will have to wait the longest or the worst case.
và để blind hoạt động, A sẽ phải chờ khoảng thời gian nhất, tương đương trường hợp tệ nhất
So this is a very slow communication protocol.
Vậy, nó là 1 giao thức rất chậm
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Yes, but it's a useful protocol
Đúng, nhưng nó hữu ích
because there are a lot of devices that are not sophisticated.
bởi có nhiều thiết bị đơn giản
And this is always going to work.
thì cách này luôn hoạt động tốt
If you know from the datasheet of device B what the specifications of device
Nếu anh biết từ datasheet của B
B are.
các thông số kĩ thuật
Let's look at another alternative.
Tới phương pháp tiếp theo
The alternative that's slightly better in my mind
Cái này tôi biết rõ hơn
is the second one which we call a busy-wait Now,
gọi là busy-wait
if device B were able to raise a flag, so if device B
Nếu thiết bị B có thể xuất cờ,
were able to raise a flag to indicate to A that the last communication you
để báo cái giao tiếp cuối
sent-- so let's say that A sends a communication and B
A gửi, giả sử, A gửi tin nhắn và B
raises a flag saying, I'm processing this.
xuất cờ báo xử lý tin nhắn
So hold on and wait until I'm finished processing.
Chờ tới khi B xử lý xong
Then A can look at that, look at that flag and keep checking the flag.
Để A có thể biết khi nào cờ tắt
And when the flag is turned off-- so when the flag is turned off,
để gửi tin nhắn tiếp theo
it then sends the next message.
lúc đó nó sẽ gửi tin tiếp theo
So it repeatedly checks the flag.
Vậy, nó liên tục check cờ
In other words, A's logic is going to look something like this,
Nói cách khác, logic của A thế này
send, check flag, and repeatedly check flag,
gửi, check cờ, và lập lại
and when identify check flag is up, and if it's up, go back check again,
Nếu cờ lên, quay sang check lại
up check again, when it's not then go back and send the next message.
nếu không có, quay sang gửi tin nhắn tiếp theo
So this is a step up.
Đây là 1 bước tiến
But now we require that device B be a little more sophisticated.
Nhưng bây giờ, ta muốn thiết bị B phức tạp hơn tí
That it can indicate to the sender and the sender
mà nó có thể báo cho người gửi
has a way of checking the flag.
để check cờ
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: But I like interrupts.
Nhưng tôi lại thích interrupts
Let's talk about interrupts.
Vậy ta nói về interrupts
Interrupts is even more sophisticated.
Interrupts thì còn phức tạp hơn
We're going to take this flag which determines the status of the device B,
Ta sẽ lấy cờ này, thể hiện trạng thái của thiết bị B
and we're going to do one more thing with this flag.
và ta sẽ làm vài thứ với nó
This flag is going to signal back to A, as a hardware event, which
Cờ này sẽ báo ngược lại cho A, như 1 event của hardware
will trigger a special software action.
mà sẽ bật tắt 1 software đặc biệt nào đó
So with interrupts the flag, the status flag of device B,
Vậy với interrupts, thì cờ trạng thái của B
which has two states, busy with the flag up and done with the flag off.
có 2 trường hợp, bận với cờ lên, và hoàn tất với cờ xuống
The busy to done state transition in B will trigger a software event in A such
Quá trình chuyển từ bận sang hoàn tất ở B sẽ bật tắt 1 software event ở A
that a special code called the interrupt service routine gets executed
mà ta gọi là interrupt service routine
on this busy to done state transition.
để xử lý
And this interrupt service routine will then perform the service,
Nó sẽ thực hiện 1 hành động
or in this case, send another message.
trong trường hợp này là gửi 1 tin nhắn khác
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So as we see, interrupts
Như ta biết, interrupts
are by far the most flexible.
thì rất tiện dụng
But they do require certain special support from the system.
Nhưng nó là yêu cầu những hỗ trợ đặc biệt từ hệ thống
And the support is in the form of this device
Chúng là khả năng
being able to interrupt the processor.
làm gián đoạn vi xử lý
And the processor should be able to suspend what its doing currently,
Và vi xử lý cũng hoãn lại
take care of this interrupt, and then resume where it left off.
và xử lý interrupt, rồi quay về chỗ cũ
And since this is a much more sophisticated technique,
Bởi vì nó khá phức tạp
not all devices support this approach.
nên không phải mọi thiết bị đều hỗ trợ
So it's not like we can choose between these.
Không phải thích là chọn
It's all about whether the support is provided
mà là thiết bị có hỗ trợ
in the particular communication system.
trong 1 hệ thống giao tiếp nào đó không
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So in this chapter,
Trong chương này
we're going to use the busy wait synchronization because it's simpler.
ta sẽ dùng đồng bộ hoá kiểu busy-wait, bởi nó đơn giản
But in the next chapter we'll have interrupts.
Nhưng ở chương sau, ta sẽ dùng interrupts
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: And by the way, there
Bằng cách này,
are two other communication ideas which are used in most advanced systems.
có 2 ý tưởng giao tiếp được dùng ở hệ thống cao cấp
They're called polling and direct memory access, or DMA.
Gọi là truy cập bộ nhớ trực tiếp, hoặc là DMA
We will not be looking at those in this class,
mà ta sẽ không đề cập đến trong khoá này
but you will encounter them if you're working
nhưng bạn sẽ gặp khi làm việc
with embedded systems in the future.
với hệ thống nhúng trong tương lai